Hi. So I'd like to talk a little bit about the people
مرحبا. اود ان أتكلم قليلا عن الناس
who make the things we use every day:
الذين يصنعون الأشياء التي نستعملها كل يوم:
our shoes, our handbags, our computers and cell phones.
أحذيتنا، حقائبنا، حواسبنا و الجوالات.
Now, this is a conversation that often calls up a lot of guilt.
الآن، هذه محادثة غالبا تستدعي الشعور بالذنب.
Imagine the teenage farm girl who makes less than
تخيل المزارعة المراهقة التي تكسب اقل من
a dollar an hour stitching your running shoes,
دولار في الساعة في خياطة حذاء الجري الخاص بك،
or the young Chinese man who jumps off a rooftop
أو الشاب الذي يقفز من على سطح
after working overtime assembling your iPad.
بعد إنهاء عمل إضافي يجمع فيه الآيباد الخاص بك.
We, the beneficiaries of globalization, seem to exploit
نحن، المستفيدين من العولمة، يبدو ان استغلال
these victims with every purchase we make,
هؤلاء الضحايا مع كل عملية شراء نقوم بها،
and the injustice
والظلم
feels embedded in the products themselves.
مُتضمن في المنتجات نفسها.
After all, what's wrong with a world in which a worker
بعد كل شيء، ما هو الخطأ في عالم يكون فيه عامل
on an iPhone assembly line can't even afford to buy one?
على خط تجميع اي فون لا يستطيع حتى شراء واحد؟
It's taken for granted that Chinese factories are oppressive,
اُتخذت كمسلمة به أن المصانع الصينية قمعية،
and that it's our desire for cheap goods
وأنه من رغبتنا في السلع الرخيصة
that makes them so.
التي تجعل منهم ذلك.
So, this simple narrative equating Western demand
لذلك، فإن هذا الحديث البسيط يساوي الطلب الغربي
and Chinese suffering is appealing,
والمعاناة الصينية جذابة،
especially at a time when many of us already feel guilty
ولا سيما في وقت يشعر الكثير منا بالفعل بالذنب
about our impact on the world,
تجاه تأثيرنا على العالم،
but it's also inaccurate and disrespectful.
لكنه أيضا غير دقيق وغير محترم.
We must be peculiarly self-obsessed to imagine that we
يجبد أن نكون غريبين مهووسين بأنفسنا لنتصور أن
have the power to drive tens of millions of people
لدينا القدرة على دفع عشرات الملايين من الناس
on the other side of the world to migrate and suffer
على الجانب الآخر من العالم على الهجرة والمعاناة
in such terrible ways.
بطرق مروعة من هذا القبيل.
In fact, China makes goods for markets all over the world,
في الواقع، الصين تصنع السلع لأسواق في جميع أنحاء العالم،
including its own, thanks to a combination of factors:
بما في ذلك اسواقها الخاصة، بسبب مجموعة من العوامل:
its low costs, its large and educated workforce,
انخفاض تكاليفها، والقوى العاملة الكبيرة المتعلمة،
and a flexible manufacturing system
ونظام تصنيع مرن
that responds quickly to market demands.
الذي يستجيب بسرعة لمتطلبات السوق.
By focusing so much on ourselves and our gadgets,
بالتركيز كثيرا على أنفسنا وأدواتنا،
we have rendered the individuals on the other end
قدنا ​​الأفراد على الطرف الآخر
into invisibility, as tiny and interchangeable
إلى الخفاء، وأن يصبحوا صغار قابلين للتبديل
as the parts of a mobile phone.
كأجزاء الهاتف المحمول.
Chinese workers are not forced into factories
العمال الصينيون لا يجبرون الى العمل في المصانع
because of our insatiable desire for iPods.
بسبب رغبتنا الجشعة لأجهزة اي بود.
They choose to leave their homes in order to earn money,
اختاروا مغادرة منازلهم من أجل كسب المال،
to learn new skills, and to see the world.
لتعلم مهارات جديدة، ورؤية العالم.
In the ongoing debate about globalization, what's
في النقاش الدائر حول العولمة، ما
been missing is the voices of the workers themselves.
كان مفقودا هو أصوات العمال أنفسهم.
Here are a few.
وهنا عدد قليل.
Bao Yongxiu: "My mother tells me to come home
Bao Yongxiu: "والدتي تقول لي أن أرجع الى البيت
and get married, but if I marry now, before I have fully
وأتزوج، ولكن إذا تزوجت الآن، قبل أن أكوّن نفسي
developed myself, I can only marry an ordinary worker,
بالكامل ، أستطيع أن أتزوج عامل عادي،
so I'm not in a rush."
لذلك أنا لست في عجلة ."
Chen Ying: "When I went home for the new year,
تشن يينغ: "وعندما ذهبت البيت للعام الجديد،
everyone said I had changed. They asked me,
الجميع قال أنني قد تغيرت. طلبوا مني،
what did you do that you have changed so much?
ماذا فعلت ليحدث لك كل هذا التغيير الكبير؟
I told them that I studied and worked hard. If you tell them
قلت لهم أنني درست وعملت بجد. إذا قلت لهم
more, they won't understand anyway."
أكثر، فلن يفهمون على أي حال. "
Wu Chunming: "Even if I make a lot of money,
Wu Chunming: "حتى لو كسبت االكثير من المال،
it won't satisfy me.
فإنها لن ترضيني.
Just to make money is not enough meaning in life."
فقط كسب المال ليس معنى كافي في الحياة."
Xiao Jin: "Now, after I get off work, I study English,
Xiao Jin: "الآن، بعد أن أحصل على إجازة من العمل، أدرس اللغة الإنجليزية،
because in the future, our customers won't
لأنه في المستقبل، عملائنا لن
be only Chinese, so we must learn more languages."
يكونون صينين فقط، لذلك يجب علينا أن نتعلم المزيد من اللغات."
All of these speakers, by the way, are young women,
كل هؤلاء المتحدثين، بالمناسبة، هم من النساء الشابات،
18 or 19 years old.
18 أو 19 سنة.
So I spent two years getting to know assembly line workers
لذلك قضيت عامين التعرف على عمال خط تجميع
like these in the south China factory city called Dongguan.
مثل هذه في مصنع مدينة جنوب الصين تسمى دونغقوان.
Certain subjects came up over and over:
بعض المواضيع تكررت مرارا:
how much money they made,
كم من المال كسبوا،
what kind of husband they hoped to marry,
أي نوع من الأزواج يأملون في الزواج،
whether they should jump to another factory
ما إذا كان ينبغي الانتقال إلى مصنع آخر
or stay where they were.
أو البقاء حيث هم.
Other subjects came up almost never, including
مواضيع أخرى لم تطرأ أبدا تقريبا، بما في ذلك
living conditions that to me looked close to prison life:
الظروف المعيشية التي بدت لي قريبة من حياة السجن:
10 or 15 workers in one room,
10 أو 15 عاملا في غرفة واحدة،
50 people sharing a single bathroom,
50 شخصا يتقاسمون حمام واحد،
days and nights ruled by the factory clock.
أيام وليال تحكمها ساعة المصنع.
Everyone they knew lived in similar circumstances,
جميع من يعرفون عاشوا في ظروف مماثلة،
and it was still better than the dormitories and homes
وكان لا يزال أفضل من المهاجع والمنازل
of rural China.
الريفية من الصين.
The workers rarely spoke about the products they made,
العمال نادرا ما تحدثوا عن المنتجات التي صنعوها،
and they often had great difficulty explaining
وكان لديهم في كثير من الأحيان صعوبة كبيرة في شرح
what exactly they did.
ما فعلوه بالضبط.
When I asked Lu Qingmin,
وقالت عندما سألت Lu Qingmin،
the young woman I got to know best,
امرأة شابة تعرفت عليها عن قرب،
what exactly she did on the factory floor,
ما فعلته بالضبط على أرضية المصنع،
she said something to me in Chinese that sounded like
قالت شيء لي في الصينية تبدو مثل
"qiu xi."
"qiu xi."
Only much later did I realize that she had been saying
فقط في وقت لاحق من ذلك بكثير أدركت أنها كانت تقول
"QC," or quality control.
"QC"، أو مراقبة الجودة.
She couldn't even tell me what she did on the factory floor.
لم تستطع حتى ان اقول لي ما فعلته في أرضية المصنع.
All she could do was parrot a garbled abbreviation
وكان كل ما يمكن أن تفعله ان تردد كالببغاء اختصارات مشوهه
in a language she didn't even understand.
في اللغة لا تفهمها.
Karl Marx saw this as the tragedy of capitalism,
كارل ماركس رأى أن هذا هو مأساة الرأسمالية،
the alienation of the worker from the product of his labor.
اغتراب العامل من نتاج عمله.
Unlike, say, a traditional maker of shoes or cabinets,
على عكس، مثلا، صانع الأحذية التقليدية أو الخزائن،
the worker in an industrial factory has no control,
العامل في مصنع لا يملك السيطرة،
no pleasure, and no true satisfaction or understanding
ولا السرور، ولا راحة حقيقية او فهم
in her own work.
في عملها.
But like so many theories that Marx arrived at
ولكن مثل العديد من النظريات التي توصل ماركس لها
sitting in the reading room of the British Museum,
جالسا في غرفة القراءة في المتحف البريطاني،
he got this one wrong.
أخطأ في هذه.
Just because a person spends her time
لمجرد ان الشخص يقضي وقته
making a piece of something does not mean
في صنع قطعة من شيء لا يعني
that she becomes that, a piece of something.
أنها تصبح ذلك، قطعة من شيء.
What she does with the money she earns,
ما تفعله بالمال الذي تكسبه ،
what she learns in that place, and how it changes her,
ما تتعلمه في ذلك المكان، وكيف يغيرها،
these are the things that matter.
هذه هي الأشياء التي تهم.
What a factory makes is never the point, and
ما ينتج مصنع ليست ابدا المقصد، و
the workers could not care less who buys their products.
العمال لا يهمهم من يشتري منتجاتهم.
Journalistic coverage of Chinese factories,
التغطية الصحفية على المصانع الصينية،
on the other hand, plays up this relationship
من ناحية أخرى، يلعب بهذه العلاقة
between the workers and the products they make.
بين العمال والمنتجات التي يقدمونها.
Many articles calculate: How long would it take
العديد من المقالات تحسب: كم من الوقت سيستغرق
for this worker to work in order to earn enough money
لهذا العامل للعمل من أجل كسب ما يكفي من المال
to buy what he's making?
لشراء ما ينتجه؟
For example, an entry-level-line assembly line worker
على سبيل المثال، عامل خط تجميع على مستوى الدخول
in China in an iPhone plant would have to shell out
في الصين في مصنع اي فون يجب أن
two and a half months' wages for an iPhone.
يوفّر شهرين ونصف من الرواتب لشراء اي فون.
But how meaningful is this calculation, really?
لكن ماذا يعني هذا الحساب، حقا؟
For example, I recently wrote an article
على سبيل المثال، كتبت مؤخرا مقالا
in The New Yorker magazine,
في مجلة نيويوركر،
but I can't afford to buy an ad in it.
ولكن لا أستطيع تحمل شراء أحد الإعلانات فيها.
But, who cares? I don't want an ad in The New Yorker,
ولكن، من يهتم؟ أنا لا أريد إعلان في مجلة نيويوركر،
and most of these workers don't really want iPhones.
ومعظم هؤلاء العمال لا يريدون حقا اي فون.
Their calculations are different.
حساباتهم مختلفة.
How long should I stay in this factory?
كم ينبغي أن ابقى في هذا المصنع؟
How much money can I save?
كم من المال يمكنني التوفير؟
How much will it take to buy an apartment or a car,
كم من الوقت سأستغرق لشراء شقة أو سيارة،
to get married, or to put my child through school?
الزواج، أو لوضع طفلي في المدرسة؟
The workers I got to know had a curiously abstract
العمال الذين تعرفت عليهم لهم علاقة
relationship with the product of their labor.
مجردة مع ماينتجون من عملهم.
About a year after I met Lu Qingmin, or Min,
نحو عام بعد أن اجتمعت مع Lu Qingmin، أو Min،
she invited me home to her family village
دعتني الى البيت الى قرية عائلتها
for the Chinese New Year.
لرأس السنة الصينية.
On the train home, she gave me a present:
على القطار إلى البيت، قدمت لي هدية:
a Coach brand change purse with brown leather trim.
محفظة نقود مع تقليم جلد بني من العلامة التجارية كوش.
I thanked her, assuming it was fake,
شكرتها، على افتراض أنها تقليد،
like almost everything else for sale in Dongguan.
مثل كل شيء آخر تقريبا للبيع في دونغقوان.
After we got home, Min gave her mother another present:
بعد وصولنا البيت،Min أعطت والدتها هدية أخرى:
a pink Dooney &amp; Bourke handbag,
حقيبة يد دووني و بورك وردية،
and a few nights later, her sister was showing off
و بعد بضع ليال لاحقه، شقيقتها كانت تعرض
a maroon LeSportsac shoulder bag.
حقيبة كتف ماروون لي سبورتساك.
Slowly it was dawning on me that these handbags
ببطء أدركت هذه حقائب اليد
were made by their factory,
تم انتاجها من قبل مصنعهم،
and every single one of them was authentic.
وكل واحد منهم كانت أصلية.
Min's sister said to her parents,
قالت شقيقة Min لوالديها،
"In America, this bag sells for 320 dollars."
"في أمريكا، هذه الحقيبة تباع ب320 دولارا".
Her parents, who are both farmers, looked on, speechless.
والديها، الذين هما مزارعين، بدوا،فاقدين الكلام.
"And that's not all -- Coach is coming out with a new line,
"وهذا ليس كل شيء - كوش ستنتج خط جديد،
2191," she said. "One bag will sell for 6,000."
"2191،" قالت. "حقيبة واحدة تباع ب 6،000."
She paused and said, "I don't know if that's 6,000 yuan or
توقفت هي وقالت: "أنا لا أعرف إذا كانت 6000 يوان أو
6,000 American dollars, but anyway, it's 6,000." (Laughter)
6000 دولار أمريكي، ولكن على أي حال، فإنه 6،000." (ضحك)
Min's sister's boyfriend, who had traveled home with her
صديق أخت Min، الذي كان قد سافر معها للبيت
for the new year, said,
للعام الجديد، قال،
"It doesn't look like it's worth that much."
"إنه لا تبدو أنها لا تستحق ذلك بكثير."
Min's sister turned to him and said, "Some people actually
أخت Min التفتت اليه وقالت "بعض الناس في الواقع
understand these things. You don't understand shit."
يفهم هذه الأشياء. أنت لا تفهم شيء".
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
In Min's world, the Coach bags had a curious currency.
في عالم Min، شنط كوش تحمل عملة غريبة.
They weren't exactly worthless, but they were nothing
لم تكن عديمة القيمة تماما، ولكنهم ليسوا قريبين بشيء
close to the actual value, because almost no one they knew
من القيمة الفعلية،لأن لا أحد تقريبا من معارفهم
wanted to buy one, or knew how much it was worth.
يريد شراء واحدة، أو يعرف كم كانت تستحق.
Once, when Min's older sister's friend got married,
مرة ، عندما تزوجت أخت Min الكبرى،
she brought a handbag along as a wedding present.
أحضرت حقيبة يد معها كهدية زفاف.
Another time, after Min had already left
مرة أخرى، بعد أن غادرت Min بالفعل
the handbag factory, her younger sister came to visit,
مصنع حقائب اليد، جاءت شقيقتها الصغرى للزيارة،
bringing two Coach Signature handbags as gifts.
أحضرت حقيبتا يد توقيع كوش كهدايا.
I looked in the zippered pocket of one,
نظرت في جيب سحاب شنطة واحدة،
and I found a printed card in English, which read,
وجدت بطاقة مطبوعة باللغة الإنجليزية، ونصها،
"An American classic.
"أميركية كلاسيكية.
In 1941, the burnished patina
في عام 1941، الغطاء المصقول
of an all-American baseball glove
من قفاز البيسبول الأمريكية
inspired the founder of Coach to create
ألهمت مؤسس كوش لإنشاء
a new collection of handbags from the same
مجموعة جديدة من حقائب اليد من نفس
luxuriously soft gloved-hand leather.
جلد القفاز الفخم اللين.
Six skilled leatherworkers crafted 12 Signature handbags
ستة دباغين مهرة أنتجوا 12 حقيبة موقعة
with perfect proportions and a timeless flair.
مع نسب الكمال والذوق الخالدة.
They were fresh, functional, and women everywhere
كانوا جديدين، عمليين، والنساء في كل مكان
adored them. A new American classic was born."
عشقوها. ميلاد جديد لأمريكان كلاسيك . "
I wonder what Karl Marx would have made of Min
أتساءل ماذا صنع كارل ماركس من Min
and her sisters.
وأخواتها.
Their relationship with the product of their labor
علاقتهم مع منتج عملهم
was more complicated, surprising and funny
كانت أكثر تعقيدا، مدهشة ومضحكة
than he could have imagined.
أكثر مما يمكن أن يتخيل.
And yet, his view of the world persists, and our tendency
وحتى الآن، رؤيته للعالم لا تزال قائمة، وميلنا
to see the workers as faceless masses,
لرؤية العمال كعديمي الوجوه،
to imagine that we can know what they're really thinking.
لنتخيل أننا يمكن أن نعرف ما يفكرون به حقا.
The first time I met Min, she had just turned 18
أول مرة التقيت Min، كانت قد بلغت للتو 18
and quit her first job on the assembly line
و تركت وظيفتها الأولى على خط التجميع
of an electronics factory.
في مصنع الالكترونيات.
Over the next two years, I watched as she switched jobs
على مدى العامين المقبلين، شاهدتها بينما غيرت وظائف
five times, eventually landing a lucrative post
خمس مرات، وفي نهاية المطاف حصلت على وظيفة مربحة
in the purchasing department of a hardware factory.
في قسم المشتريات لمصنع أجهزة.
Later, she married a fellow migrant worker,
في وقت لاحق، تزوجت زميل مهاجر،
moved with him to his village,
انتقلت معه إلى قريته،
gave birth to two daughters,
أنجبت ابنتين،
and saved enough money to buy a secondhand Buick
وجمعت ما يكفي من المال لشراء بويك مستعمل
for herself and an apartment for her parents.
لنفسها وشقة لوالديها.
She recently returned to Dongguan on her own
هي عادت مؤخرا إلى دونغقوان لوحدها
to take a job in a factory that makes construction cranes,
لتأخذ وظيفة في مصنع ينتج رافعات البناء،
temporarily leaving her husband and children
تاركة مؤقتا زوجها وأطفالها
back in the village.
في القرية.
In a recent email to me, she explained,
في رسالة بريد إلكتروني قريبه لي، أوضحت
"A person should have some ambition while she is young
"الشخص يجب أن يكون طموح في شبابه
so that in old age she can look back on her life
حتى في سن الشيخوخة يمكنها أن تنظر إلى الوراء على حياتها
and feel that it was not lived to no purpose."
وتشعر أنك لم تعيش بدون هدف."
Across China, there are 150 million workers like her,
عبر الصين، هناك 150 مليون عامل مثلها،
one third of them women, who have left their villages
ثلثهم من النساء، الذين تركوا قراهم
to work in the factories, the hotels, the restaurants
للعمل في المصانع والفنادق، والمطاعم
and the construction sites of the big cities.
ومواقع البناء في المدن الكبيرة.
Together, they make up the largest migration in history,
جميعا، يشكلون أكبر هجرة في التاريخ،
and it is globalization, this chain that begins
والعولمة، هذه السلسلة التي تبدأ
in a Chinese farming village
في قرية زراعية صينية
and ends with iPhones in our pockets and Nikes on our feet
وتنتهي مع أجهزة اي فون في جيوبنا وأحذية نايكي على أقدامنا
and Coach handbags on our arms
وحقائب يد كوش على أذرعنا
that has changed the way these millions of people
التي غيرت طريقة عمل ملايين من الناس
work and marry and live and think.
وزواجهم وحياتهم وتفكيرهم.
Very few of them would want to go back
عدد قليل جدا منهم يريدون العودة
to the way things used to be.
إلى الأشياء بطريقة معتادة.
When I first went to Dongguan, I worried that
عندما ذهبت لأول مرة إلى دونغقوان،أنا قلقت
it would be depressing to spend so much time with workers.
من احتمال الاكتئاب جراء قضاء الكثير من الوقت مع العمال.
I also worried that nothing would ever happen to them,
كنت قلقة أيضا أن لا شيء يمكن أن يحدث ابداً لهم،
or that they would have nothing to say to me.
أو أنه لن يكون لهم اي شيء يقولونه لي.
Instead, I found young women who were smart and funny
بدلا من ذلك، وجدت الشابات كانوا اذكياء ومضحكين
and brave and generous.
وشجعان وكرماء.
By opening up their lives to me,
من خلال فتح حياتهم لي،
they taught me so much about factories
لقد علموني الكثير عن المصانع
and about China and about how to live in the world.
وعن الصين وحول كيفية العيش في العالم.
This is the Coach purse that Min gave me
هذي هي هدية الكوش التي أهدتني اياها Min
on the train home to visit her family.
على القطار في الطريق لزيارة عائلتها.
I keep it with me to remind me of the ties that tie me
أبقيها معي لتذكيري بالروابط التي تربطني
to the young women I wrote about,
بالشابات التي كتبت عنهم،
ties that are not economic but personal in nature,
روابط ليست اقتصادية بل شخصية في طبيعتها،
measured not in money but in memories.
لا تقاس بالمال لكن بالذكريات.
This purse is also a reminder that the things that you imagine,
هذا محفظة أيضاً ذكرى بأن الأشياء التي تتخيل،
sitting in your office or in the library,
جالساً في مكتبك أو في المكتبة،
are not how you find them when you actually go out
ليسوا كما تجدهم عندما تذهب فعلا
into the world.
إلى العالم.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Thank you, Leslie, that was an insight
كريس أندرسون: شكرا لكي، ليزلي، هذه نظرة
that a lot of us haven't had before.
الكثير منا لم يفكر بها من قبل.
But I'm curious. If you had a minute, say,
لكن أنا أتسائل. إذا كان لديك دقيقة، لنفترض،
with Apple's head of manufacturing,
مع مدير الانتاج في شركة أبل،
what would you say?
ماذا كنت ستقولين؟
Leslie Chang: One minute?
ليزلي تشانغ: دقيقة واحدة؟
CA: One minute. (Laughter)
ك.أ. : دقيقة واحدة. (ضحك)
LC: You know, what really impressed me about the workers
ل. ت : أنت تعرف، ما أعجبني حقا عن العمال
is how much they're self-motivated, self-driven,
هو كم انهم لديهم دوافع ذاتية، دافعين أنفسهم،
resourceful, and the thing that struck me,
وسيعين الحيلة، والشيء الذي أبهرني،
what they want most is education, to learn,
ما يريدون أكثر من غيره هو التعليم، والتعلم،
because most of them come from very poor backgrounds.
لأن معظمهم يأتي من بيئة فقيرة جدا.
They usually left school when they were in 7th or 8th grade.
عادة يتركون المدرسة عندما كانوا في الصف 7 أو 8.
Their parents are often illiterate,
والديهم غالبا أمييون،
and then they come to the city, and they, on their own,
بعد ذلك يأتون إلى المدينة، و هم، من تلقاء نفسهم،
at night, during the weekends, they'll take a computer class,
في الليل، خلال عطلة نهاية الأسبوع، يأخذون درس حاسب آلي،
they'll take an English class, and learn
درس لغة إنجليزية، ويتعلمون
really, really rudimentary things, you know,
حقا، حقا بدائية الأشياء، كما تعلمون،
like how to type a document in Word,
مثل كيفية كتابة مستند في وورد،
or how to say really simple things in English.
أو كيف يقولون أشياء بسيطة حقا في اللغة الإنجليزية.
So, if you really want to help these workers,
لذا، إذا كنت تريد حقا أن تساعد هؤلاء العمال،
start these small, very focused, very pragmatic classes
تبدأ فصول، مركزة جدا، صغيرة
in these schools, and what's going to happen is,
في هذه المدارس، وما سيحدث هو،
all your workers are going to move on,
جميع العاملين لديك سيمضون قدما،
but hopefully they'll move on into higher jobs within Apple,
ولكن نأمل أنهم سوف ينتقلون إلى وظائف أعلى داخل أبل،
and you can help their social mobility
وأنت تساعد على حراكهم الاجتماعي
and their self-improvement.
وعلى تحسين ذواتهم .
When you talk to workers, that's what they want.
عندما تتحدث إلى العمال، هذا ما يريدونه.
They do not say, "I want better hot water in the showers.
انهم لا يقولون: "أريد ماء ساخن أفضل في الاستحمام.
I want a nicer room. I want a TV set."
أريد غرفة أجمل. أريد جهاز تلفزيون."
I mean, it would be nice to have those things,
أعني، سيكون من الجميل أن تحصل على تلك الأشياء،
but that's not why they're in the city,
ولكن هذا ليس سبب وجودهم في المدينة،
and that's not what they care about.
وهذا ليس ما يهمهم.
CA: Was there a sense from them of a narrative that
ك.أ : هل كان هناك شعور منهم عبر القصص
things were kind of tough and bad, or was there a narrative
بأن الأمور كانت صعبة وسيئة، أو كان هناك رواية
of some kind of level of growth, that things over time
على شاكلة نمو في المستوى، بحيث أن الأمور مع مرور الوقت
were getting better?
ستتحسن إلى الأفضل؟
LC: Oh definitely, definitely. I mean, you know,
ل . ت : أوه بالتأكيد، بالتأكيد. أعني، أنت تعرف،
it was interesting, because I spent basically two years
أنه كان مثيرا للاهتمام، لأنني في الأساس قضيت سنتين
hanging out in this city, Dongguan,
هائمة في هذه المدينة، دونغقوان،
and over that time, you could see immense change
وخلال تلك الفترة ، تستطيع أن ترى التغيير الهائل
in every person's life: upward, downward, sideways,
في حياة كل شخص: التصاعدي، التنازلي، جانبيا،
but generally upward.
ولكن عموما التصاعدي.
If you spend enough time, it's upward, and I met people
إذا قضيت ما يكفي من الوقت، فإنه إلى أعلى، والتقيت أناس
who had moved to the city 10 years ago, and who are now
انتقلوا إلى المدينة قبل 10 سنوات، والذين هم الآن
basically urban middle class people,
أصبحوا أناس من الطبقة الوسطى في الحضر،
so the trajectory is definitely upward.
وبالتالي فإن المسار هو بالتأكيد لأعلى.
It's just hard to see when you're suddenly
لكن الشيء الصعب هو أن نرى عندما فجأة
sucked into the city. It looks like everyone's poor and
تمتص في المدينة. يبدو الجميع فقراء و
desperate, but that's not really how it is.
بائسين، ولكن هذا ليس حقا .
Certainly, the factory conditions are really tough,
ومن المؤكد أن ظروف العمل في المصنع هي صعبة حقا،
and it's nothing you or I would want to do,
وأنه شيء لا أنا أو أنت نريد أن نعمل،
but from their perspective, where they're coming from
ولكن من وجهة نظرهم، من حيث أتوا
is much worse, and where they're going
هو أسوأ بكثير، وذاهبون
is hopefully much better, and I just wanted to give
آملين إلى ما هو أفضل بكثير، وأنا أردت فقط إعطاء
that context of what's going on in their minds,
هذا السياق عن ما يجري في عقولهم،
not what necessarily is going on in yours.
وليس بالضرورة ما يجري في عقولكم.
CA: Thanks so much for your talk.
ك. أ : شكرا جزيلا لمحادثتك.
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا. (تصفيق)